Guide to the Narodno-Trudovoj Sojuz Papers [National Alliance of Russian Solidarists]
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Narodno-Trudovoj Sojuz papers
1951-1968
MS 608
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
(1 box)
A collection of pamphlets, brochures, leaflets, and newspapers published by the Narodno-Trudovoj Sojuz [National Alliance of Russian Solidarists], an organization founded in 1930 by anti-communist Russian émigrés whose goal was to overthrow the Russian government.
Narodno-trudovoĭ soi︠u︡z
Scope and Contents
This collection contains numerous pamphlets and brochures published by Possev [ The Sowing ], a Russian anti-communist weekly, which works in close touch with the NTS. Possev prints practically all of the NTS publications, a percentage of which are produced on special thin paper for circulation and distribution to Soviet citizens. The brochures and pamphlets in this collection are arranged alphabetically by author and by title when there is no author indicated. There are 99 leaflets included here; some are the sample copies of the type that were circulated inside the USSR.
There are also numerous folders of camouflage publications: i.e., numerous works that were produced under the cover of harmless titles of known literary works. A few contained in this collection were simply camouflaged as Soviet works. They are arranged alphabetically by author of the literary work with the anti-communist publication in parentheses. There are some false numbers of Soviet daily papers which were circulated with the contents entirely drafted by the NTS propaganda service. All the material contained within this collection is in Russian except three folders of NTS marerial in English and one folder of NTS material in German.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The NTS (Narodno-Trudovoj Sojuz [National Alliance of Russian Solidarists]) was established by Russian émigré students in European universities in 1930. They wished to oppose the Bolshevik ideology and its inhuman methods in Russia and the passivity of the older émigrés.
The organization aimed to be an internal Russian oppositionary force. Their final goal was to overthrow Soviet Communism and to establish freedom and democracy. They wished to penetrate Russia with ideas (they spread their first leaflets in 1935) and with men (in 1932 the first NTS members illegally crossed the Russian border).
Despite endless obstruction by the Germans, during the war most of the NTS members crossed into German-occupied Russia and by 1943 had established 120 NTS groups in 54 Russian towns. At the end of the war more than 200 NTS members were in German concentration camps, one-third of whom were to be "liberated" by Soviet troops only to exchange Hitler's camps for Stalin's.
Out of the chaos of the end of the war NTS emerged with an extensive base of supporters both inside and outside Russia, with a definite understanding of the need to replace the Communist system of terror with a radically different one.
Anti-communist movements; Europe; Soviet Union -- Politics and government -- 1936-1953; Narodno-trudovoĭ soi︠u︡z
- Inventory
  - BROCHURES
    - Artemov, A. "The People and the Regime." Possev, 1953, 32 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Garanin, E. I. "How to Lead the Struggle." Possev, 1958, 52 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Nikolin, A. "The Truth about Poland." n.d., 31 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Kungurtsev, V. "The Communist Party and Christianity." Possev, 1960, 64 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Nemirov, A. "Youth, Strivings and Struggles." 1959, 48 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Romanov, E. R. "The Situation in Russia and the Condition of Revolutionary Strength." Possev, 1958, 80 pp. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Zalevskij, M. "For Free Labor." Possev, 1958 (52 pp.) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Agriculture Today and Tomorrow." 1957, 48 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "An Answer to the Slanderers." n.d., 17 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "A Short Guide and Index: Vsemirnaja Vystavka [World's Fair]." 1958, 29 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Decide According to Your Conscience." n.d., 100 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "For Russia! NST." n.d., 17 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Our School is Now Even in New Russia." 1957, 32 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Radio Station "Free Russia." 1959, 20 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Radio Station "Free Russia." n.d., 32 pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "Russia After the 20th Congress of the KPSS." 1956, 31 pp. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Path Towards Freedom." 1956, 96 pp. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Power and the People After the 20th Congress." Possev, 1957, 107 pp. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "The Truth about Hungary." 1957, 96 pp. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - PAMPHLETS
    - Vyšeslavtsev, B. P. "Dialectical Materialism." n.d., 29 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - An Open Letter to M. Mihajlova. n.d., 54 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Appeal of the Narodno-Trudovoj Sojuz." 1958, 16 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Citizens of Our Homeland." 1959, 6 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Citizens of Russia." n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Comrade!" 1957, 32 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Decide According to Your Conscience." 1967, 31 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Decide According to Your Conscience," 2nd Edition. n.d., 28 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Friend! Comrade!" n.d., 8 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Program of the NTS. Miniature publication, 1962, 37 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "To All the Citizens of Our Homeland." n.d., 6 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "To the People of Russia." 1957, 8 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Sfinxi [The Sphinx]." 1965, 28 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Solidarism - The Idea of the Future." n.d., 28 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Urgent Task." n.d., 6 pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Leaflets of the Narodno-Trudovoj Sojuz. 1953-1960. 99 leaflets. One-, two-, three-, and four-page leaflets. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CAMOUFLAGE PUBLICATIONS
    - Gogol, N.V., Inspector General. Gosudarstvennoje Izdatel'stvo Xudožestvennoj Literatury, Moskva, 1952. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      General
      (Poremskij, V. "Problems of a National Revolution." 1952, 74 pp.)
    - Gorbatov, B. Daša. Izdatel'stvo Pravda. Moskva, 1957, 36 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Korolenko, V.G. "In An Evil Society." Gosudarstvennoje Izdatel'stvo Xudožestvennoj Literatury, Moskva, 1950. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (Artemov, A. "About Solidarity." 1953, 43 pp.)
    - Nikitin, A. "Attack." Gospolitizdat, Moskva, 1959. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (Garanin, E. I. "How to Lead the Struggle." 1959, 72 pp.)
    - Poljanovskij, V. Ja. "In The Interest of the People." Gospolitizdat, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (Gutšin, A. "Problems of the Anti-Communist Struggle." 1958, 32 pp.)
    - Sokolovskij, V. "Sailors." Izdatel'stvo Vodnogo Transporta, Moskva, n.d., 47 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "For Free Labor!" Prolizdat, Moskva, 1958, 15 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Main Role of the Foremost Ideas." Izdat. Pravda, Moskva, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      ("Decide According to Your Conscience." 1958, 100 pp.)
    - "The Problems of Our Struggle." Gosvojenizdat, Moskva, 1957, 50 pp. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - NEWSPAPERS
    - Blank dlja zakazov [ Order Application ]. International Book, Oct 1952. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Komsomol'skaja Pravda [ Komsomol (Young Communist League) Truth ], 8 May 1955. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Literaturnaja Gazeta [ Literary Newspaper ], special issue, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Pravda [ Truth ], 7 Nov 1957. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sovetskaja Armija [ Soviet Army ], 27 Aug 1950. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sovetskaja Baltika [ The Soviet Baltic ], 15 Mar 1956. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Vestnik [ Herald ], No. 2 1954. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Volja [ Freedom ]
      - Nos. 1-14; 1961-1962. (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
      - Nos. 18-20; 1963. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - No. 24, 25; 1964. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - No. 26, 28, 29; 1965. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Possev [Russian anti-communist weekly]
      - [No. ?]; 31 May, 12 July 1953. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - No. 16; Sep - Oct 1954. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Nos. 17-24; Feb - Dec 1955. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - No. 1, 2 (special); 1956. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Nos. 1-7, 10; Jan - Sep 1956. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - No. 10; Dec 1956. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Nos. 2-5, [?]; Feb - Jun 1957. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - [No. ?]; Dec 1958. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Pravda Soldata [ The Soldier's Truth ]
      - No. 5, 14; Mar, Nov 1956. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Nos. 18-22; Aug - Nov 1958. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Nos. 1-3, 4 (special), 5; Jan - Jun 1959. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Izvestija Pravdy [ The News of the Truth ]
      - No. 1, 2; 15, 30 Apr 1951. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - No. 24, 28, 29; 25 May, 30 Jul, 13 Aug 1952. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - No. 47; 25 Jul 1953. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - No. 71; 1 Oct 1954. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Vaxta Svobody [ The Watch For Freedom ]
      - No. 1, 2, 2a (special); Jul - Sep, [?] 1956. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - No. 5, 1958. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - No. 6, 7; 1959. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "NTS" MATERIAL IN ENGLISH
    - NTS,, 57 pp., 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - NTS,, 16 pp., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Russian Today and Tomorrow,", 162 pp., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "The Trial of Gerald Brooke and the NTS," n.d., 32 pp. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - The Bell [bi-monthly organ of the Foreign Friends of NTS]
      - Nos. 1-4; Jan - Jul 1967. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - No. 6; Nov 1967. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - No. 1, 2; Jan, Mar 1968. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - LEAFLETS
    - "For Peace," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "New Soviet Crime," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Peoples of America," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Stalin is Dead," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "NTS" MATERIAL IN GERMAN
    - "Probleme der Freiheit in Russland," n.d., 20 pp. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Wollen die Russen den Kommunismus?" n.d., 16 pp. (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Willst du Stalin helfen die Welt zu erobern?" n.d., 1 p. (Box 1, Folder 19)